<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Daniel Hurley - Network Systems Biology</title>
    <description>Daniel Hurley - Network Systems Biology</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 16 Mar 2016 13:23:34 +1100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Mar 2016 13:23:34 +1100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>A general language for networks</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;newthought&quot;&gt;Network models have great potential&lt;/span&gt;  to uncover complex interactions and pathways not visible by other methods, but network modelling is still an ad hoc activity, with no general theory to relate different approaches, &lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;In Depth: &lt;a href=&quot;http://danielghurley.github.io/grammarofnetworks&quot;&gt;watch a web presentation of this work&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;  nor principles for determining what a network tells us about the biology that created it.&lt;!--more--&gt;  Progress in data-driven ‘network biology’ has been hampered by the lack of a general language for integrating different network methods from different domains of knowledge.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To overcome these obstacles, I am developing a &lt;em&gt;grammar of network methods&lt;/em&gt;, an empirical grammar of data manipulation extended into graph theory.   The grammar is influenced by the statistical graphics work of Wilkinson&lt;sup class=&quot;sidenote-number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;sidenote-number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; See &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/0-387-28695-0&quot;&gt;The Grammar of Graphics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; and Wickham&lt;sup class=&quot;sidenote-number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;sidenote-number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; See &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1198/jcgs.2009.07098&quot;&gt;A Layered Grammar of Graphics&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.18637/jss.v059.i10&quot;&gt;Tidy Data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, and allows us to describe the structure of different network methods (like the syntax in a human grammar) and relate them directly back to the biological data used to create the network, in order to uncover biological meaning (semantics).   Using simple graph elements and a declarative syntax, the grammar is able to describe existing network modelling in biology using a common set of concepts, focused particularly on network inference from genomic, proteomic and metabolomic data.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;newthought&quot;&gt;The grammar of network methods&lt;/span&gt;  is a new research direction stemming from work started during my PhD, where I integrated diverse mathematical and statistical methods of reverse-engineering transcriptomic networks&lt;sup class=&quot;sidenote-number&quot;&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;sidenote-number&quot;&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkr902&quot;&gt;The initial computational framework&lt;/a&gt; was written in MATLAB&lt;/span&gt;, and applied these methods to generate and validate experimental hypotheses in transformed cell lines&lt;sup class=&quot;sidenote-number&quot;&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;sidenote-number&quot;&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt; Applications in &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0034247&quot;&gt;melanoma prognosis&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkr902&quot;&gt;endothelial cell biology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.  The grammar develops this work by describing these existing analysis methods using a common language, and showing clearly their similarities and differences.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specifically, my current research implements the grammar in two programming languages common in systems and computational biology (R and Python), and uses it to answer two major open questions in computational biology: the unification of ‘knowledge-based’ and ‘data-driven’ network methods, and the effect of ensemble network methods (the ‘wisdom of crowds’ effect).  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;newthought&quot;&gt;Completing this work&lt;/span&gt;  will transform network modelling in biology, from an ad hoc activity where different methods exist in isolation from one another, into a principled, evidence-driven activity with heuristics for which methods are fruitful on which data for which outcomes.     &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;featured-publications&quot;&gt;Featured publications&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hurley, D. G.&lt;/strong&gt;, Cursons, J., Wang, Y. K., Budden, D. M., Print, C. G., &amp;amp; Crampin, E. J. (2014). &lt;a href=&quot;http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/content/31/2/277.abstract&quot;&gt;NAIL, a software toolset for inferring, analyzing and visualizing regulatory networks&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Bioinformatics&lt;/em&gt;, 31(2), 277–278. doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btu612&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hurley, D.&lt;/strong&gt;, Araki, H., Tamada, Y., Dunmore, B., Sanders, D., Humphreys, S., … Print, C. G. (2012). &lt;a href=&quot;http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/doi/10.1093/nar/gkr902&quot;&gt;Gene network inference and visualization tools for biologists: application to new human transcriptome datasets&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Nucleic Acids Research&lt;/em&gt;, 40(6), 2377–2398. doi:10.1093/nar/gkr902&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 16 Mar 2016 00:06:04 +1100</pubDate>
        <link>/articles/16/grammar-of-networks</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/articles/16/grammar-of-networks</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Applied network modelling</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;newthought&quot;&gt;Data-driven network models&lt;/span&gt;  can be applied to answer specific questions in experimental biology using genomic, transcriptomic and proteomic data.  &lt;!--more--&gt;Collaborating with experimental researchers, I have developed network modelling approaches to guide experimental research in drug development&lt;sup class=&quot;sidenote-number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;sidenote-number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; With colleagues at the Auckland Cancer Society Research Centre &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.bcp.2014.03.001&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1158/1538-7445.AM2013-2111&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, in signalling pathways in human skin&lt;sup class=&quot;sidenote-number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;sidenote-number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; With colleagues at the Auckland Bioengineering Institute &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/s12918-015-0187-6&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/s13742-015-0102-5&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, and in neurochemistry&lt;sup class=&quot;sidenote-number&quot;&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;sidenote-number&quot;&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; With colleagues at the Centre for Brain Research &lt;a href=&quot;10.1186/1742-2094-11-104&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;featured-publications&quot;&gt;Featured publications&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cursons J., Gao J., (Joint first authorship). &lt;strong&gt;Hurley D.G.&lt;/strong&gt;, Dunbar P.R., Jacobs M.D., Crampin E.J. &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/s12918-015-0187-6&quot;&gt;Regulation of ERK-MAPK signaling in human epidermis&lt;/a&gt;. BMC Syst Biol. 2015;9(1):41.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hunter, F. W., Jaiswal, J. K., &lt;strong&gt;Hurley, D. G.&lt;/strong&gt;, Liyanage, H. D., McManaway, S. P., Gu, Y., others. (2014). &lt;a href=&quot;http://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S0006295214001592&quot;&gt;The flavoprotein FOXRED2 reductively activates nitro-chloromethylbenzindolines and other hypoxia-targeting prodrugs&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Biochemical Pharmacology&lt;/em&gt;, 89(2), 224–235.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jansson, D., Rustenhoven, J., Feng, S., &lt;strong&gt;Hurley, D.&lt;/strong&gt;, Oldfield, R. L., Bergin, P. S., … Dragunow, M. (2014). &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jneuroinflammation.com/content/11/1/104&quot;&gt;A role for human brain pericytes in neuroinflammation&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Neuroinflammation&lt;/em&gt;, 11(1), 104.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wang, J., Guise, C. P., Hsu, H.-L., &lt;strong&gt;Hurley, D.&lt;/strong&gt;, Wilson, W. R., &amp;amp; Patterson, A. V. (2013). &lt;a href=&quot;http://cancerres.aacrjournals.org/lookup/doi/10.1158/1538-7445.AM2013-2111&quot;&gt;Identification of reductases capable of metabolic activation of hypoxia targeting prodrug SN30000 and hypoxia marker EF5&lt;/a&gt;. In &lt;em&gt;Cancer Research&lt;/em&gt; (Vol. 73, pp. 2111–2111)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 16 Mar 2016 00:06:04 +1100</pubDate>
        <link>/articles/16/applied-network-modelling</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/articles/16/applied-network-modelling</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Research reproducibility</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;newthought&quot;&gt;Computational methods&lt;/span&gt;  should be among the most reproducible methods in the life sciences; &lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;First Look: &lt;a href=&quot;http://danielghurley.github.io/reference_environments&quot;&gt;watch a web presentation of this work&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;  the environment and protocol for a computational method can be specified to a much greater degree, and with much greater precision, than a typical laboratory method.&lt;!--more--&gt;  Unfortunately, many published computational results remain hard to reproduce, and methods are often not specified in sufficient detail to replicate or re-implement.  I have proposed  techniques for building &lt;em&gt;reference environments&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;sidenote-number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;sidenote-number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; Little bootstrapped open-source virtual environments for reproducing a single computational result.&lt;/span&gt; enabling researchers to reproduce computational results precisely, with minimal effort, and implemented these for a range of results in computational biology&lt;sup class=&quot;sidenote-number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;sidenote-number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; Lots of published &lt;a href=&quot;http://uomsystemsbiology.github.io/research/reference-environments/#examples-of-reference-environments&quot;&gt;examples here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://uomsystemsbiology.github.io/research/reference-environments&quot;&gt;My current research in this theme&lt;/a&gt; extends this approach and set of tools to work across all major languages (R/Python/Java/MATLAB/Fortran/C) and platforms in systems and computational biology.  The method produces reference environments across three different reproducibility platforms: as a virtual machine, as a container, and as a cloud environment, all from a single set of configuration scripts.  Reference environments integrate readily with other reproducible research technologies, and can contain any type of language or computation.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;newthought&quot;&gt;The reference environment approach&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;How do reference environments relate to other types of &amp;#8216;reproducible research&amp;#8217;?  &lt;a href=&quot;http://uomsystemsbiology.github.io/research/reference-environments/#how-reference-environments-relate-to-other-reproducible-research-tools&quot;&gt;I discuss that here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;  explicitly separates the core scientific findings of a piece of computational research from the software implementation in which they are embedded, and allows readers and reviewers to choose the most appropriate implementation type for their situation.  Reference environments &lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8220;But why not just use &amp;lt;currently popular reproducibility tool/website&amp;gt;?&amp;#8221;  &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/bib/bbu043&quot;&gt;I discuss that here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;  also have many applications in more general reproducibility; providing standard environments for testing or benchmarking, or in teaching to accelerate students&amp;#8217; hands-on experience with tools and languages.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://danielghurley.github.io/reference_environments&quot;&gt;Watch a web presentation of this work here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;featured-publications&quot;&gt;Featured publications&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hurley, D. G.&lt;/strong&gt;, Budden, D. M., &amp;amp; Crampin, E. J. (2014). &lt;a href=&quot;http://bib.oxfordjournals.org/content/early/2014/12/06/bib.bbu043.abstract&quot;&gt;Virtual Reference Environments: a simple way to make research reproducible&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Briefings in Bioinformatics&lt;/em&gt;, bbu043. doi:10.1093/bib/bbu043&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jun 2015 23:06:04 +1000</pubDate>
        <link>/articles/15/reproducible-research</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/articles/15/reproducible-research</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
